A Guide to the Markle Foundation records, Record Group 1-Record Group 3 FA024
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Markle Foundation Programs, 1
  - Markle Foundation Programs - Accession 1, 1; 41 Cubic Feet
    - Communications, 1969-1984; 3; 30 Cubic Feet 68 boxes
      - Middlebury College - Kimberly Sparks, 1976-1979 (Box 44, Folder 313)
        Program grant G77003. Support of the adaptation of German and Spanish language versions of "Sesame Street" television programs for use in beginning language courses. $34,344 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976.
      - University of Minnesota Foundation - F. Gerald Kline, 1977-1979 (Box 44, Folder 314)
        Discretionary grant D79147. To support a meeting of the National News Council to be hosted by the School of Journalism & Mass Communications. $3,025, awarded on September 13, 1978.
      - University of Minnesota Foundation - Daniel Wackman, 1974-1978 (Box 44, Folder 315)
        Program grant D75004. To pursue research on the ways in which children are influenced by pro-social television content. $92,298, awarded on November 22, 1974.
      - University of Missouri - School of Medicine - William Mayer, 1970-1976 (Box 44, Folder 316)
        Program grant. Educational Resources Group. Support for development of educational resources for medical schools. $143,000, awarded on March 12, 1970.
      - MITRE Corporation - Robert Everett, 1970-1971 (Box 44, Folder 317)
        Program grant. Research on requirements for fully developed cable television systems in urban settings. $250,000, awarded on March 16, 1971. Program grant. Research on broadband telecommunications cable systems. $50,000, awarded on November 12, 1971.
      - MITRE Corporation - Robert Everett, 1970-1971 (Box 44, Folder 318)
      - MITRE Corporation - Robert Everett, 1970-1971 (Box 44, Folder 319)
      - Modern Language Association - William Schaefer, 1975-1976 (Box 45, Folder 320)
        Discretionary grant D76001. To support a feasibility study for an intellectual newspaper serving the MLA constituency. $10,000, awarded on August 4, 1975.
      - National Association of Educational Broadcasters - James Fellows, 1976 (Box 45, Folder 321)
        Discretionary grant. Management development program. In support of an advanced management development program to be conducted at the Harvard Graduate School of Business Administration. $5,000, awarded on May 5, 1976.
      - National Association of Educational Broadcasters - William Harley, 1970-1975 (Box 45, Folder 322)
        Discretionary grant D75027. For development of a program information clearing house. $5,000, awarded on April 4, 1975.
      - National Black Media Coalition - Ted Carpenter, 1976 (Box 45, Folder 323)
        Discretionary grant D77005. Long range funding proposal. Interim general support. $6,000, awarded on October 29, 1976.
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Nick Johnson and Ted Carpenter, 1976-1980 (Box 45, Folder 324)
        Program grant G77004. Support of experiments to monitor television for violent content and to develop a new model for TV audience ratings. $54,125 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976.
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Nick Johnson and Ted Carpenter, 1976-1980 (Box 45, Folder 325)
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Nick Johnson and Ted Carpenter, 1976-1980 (Box 45, Folder 326)
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Ted Carpenter, 1976-June 1977 (Box 45, Folder 327)
        Program grant G77016. General support to continue and strengthen it as an advocate for the public interest in broadcasting. $55,000 ($35,000 fy 1977, $20,000 fy 1978), awarded on November 23, 1976.
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Ted Carpenter, 1976-June 1977 (Box 45, Folder 328)
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Ted Carpenter, July 1977-1980 (Box 46, Folder 329)
      - National Citizen's Committee on Broadcasting - Ted Carpenter, July 1977-1980 (Box 46, Folder 330)
      - National Council for the Advancement of Education Writing - Cynthia Parsons, 1970-1977 (Box 46, Folder 331)
      - National Council for the Advancement of Education Writing - Cynthia Parsons, 1970-1977 (Box 46, Folder 332)
      - National Council on the Aging - Louis Hausman, 1975-1978 (Box 46, Folder 333)
        Discretionary grant D78335. To maintain the West Coast office while seeking outside funding in support of their program to encourage media professionals to present more realistic portrayals of older persons. $18,000, awarded on May 23, 1978.
      - National Council on the Aging - Jack Ossovsky, 1977-1980 (Box 46, Folder 334)
        Program grant G76015. In support of a West Coast Representative. $173,340 ($21,000 fy 1976, $81,000 fy 1977, $71,340 fy 1978), awarded March 12, 1976.
      - National Council on the Aging, 1977-1980 (Box 46, Folder 334B)
      - National Endowment for the Humanities - Joseph Slater, 1973-1975 (Box 46, Folder 335)
        Discretionary grant. Aspen Institute/cable television. Matching grant to the Aspen Institute Cable Workshop. $11,350, awarded on August 3, 1973.
      - National Federation of Community Broadcasters - Tom Thomas, 1975-August 1977 (Box 46, Folder 336)
        Program grant G78103. Support of a program to expand and improve work on policy issues relating to non-commercial radio. $33,200 ($18,200 fy 1978, $15,000 fy 1979), awarded on November 28, 1977.
      - National Federation of Community Broadcasters - Tom Thomas, August 1977-1980 (Box 47, Folder 337)
        Program grant G79257. Non-commercial FM rulemaking. To continue work on policy issues concerning noncommercial radio. $35,000 ($15,000 fy 1979, $20,000 fy 1980), awarded on March 22, 1979.
      - National Federation of Community Broadcasters - Tom Thomas, August 1977-1980 (Box 47, Folder 338)
      - National Friends of Public Broadcasting - Frances Shuman, 1970-1976 (Box 47, Folder 339)
        Discretionary grant. Support for work in encouraging citizen support of public broadcasting at the local level. $20,000, awarded on March 6, 1973.
      - National Friends of Public Broadcasting - Frances Shuman, 1970-1976 (Box 47, Folder 340)
      - National News Council - William Arthur, 1973-1977 (Box 47, Folder 341)
        Program grants G76004, G76019. To support a national press council (Funds transferred from grant to Twentieth Century Fund, June 15, 1972). $100,000, awarded on November 5, 1973. Program grant. General support. $125,000, awarded on June 11, 1974. Program grant. To further operation and development of the National News Council. $100,000 fy 1976, awarded June 20, 1975. Program grant. In support of further operation and development of a media review council. $300,000 ($100,000 fy 1977, $100,000 fy 1978, $100,000 fy 1979), awarded on March 12, 1976.
      - National News Council - William Arthur, 1973-1977 (Box 47, Folder 342)
      - National News Council - William Arthur, 1973-1977 (Box 47, Folder 343)
      - National News Council - William Arthur, 1973-1977 (Box 47, Folder 344)
      - National News Council - William Arthur, 1978-1980 (Box 48, Folder 345)
      - National Opinion Research Center - Andrew Greeley, 1976-1979 (Box 48, Folder 346)
        Program grant G77010. Media symbols. Support for a study of the ethnic press and radio. $91,400, awarded on March 16, 1972. Program grant. Support of exploratory research on the relationship between the mass media and the ways in which young Americans think about themselves and their society. $34,700 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976.
      - National Radio Theatre of Chicago - Alvin Spector, 1978-1982 (Box 48, Folder 347)
        D79259.
      - New School for Social Research - Herbert Danska, 1975-July 1978 (Box 48, Folder 348)
        Program grant G77014. Support of a feasibility study of means of improving local public affairs programming on television through joint commercial and non-commercial funding. $116,000 ($58,000 fy 1977, $58,000 fy 1978), awarded on November 23, 1976.
      - New School for Social Research - Herbert Danska, 1975-July 1978 (Box 48, Folder 349)
      - New School for Social Research - Herbert Danska, 1975-July 1978 (Box 48, Folder 350)
      - New School for Social Research, 1977 (Box 49, Folder 351)
        Local public affairs programming. Report.
      - New York City Voluntary Action Corporation - Winifred Brown, 1976-1977 (Box 49, Folder 352)
        Discretionary grant. Funds for producing a TV videotape spot for volunteer recruitment. $3,000, awarded on January 18, 1977.
        Film entitled "Mayor's Voluntary Action Center." 30 second TV public service spot promoting volunteer recruitment. 1 reel. Labeled "IV 3 B6 F1," located in Film Vault, Unit 1, Shelf 2 as of 1993.
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, 1970-January 1975 (Box 49, Folder 353)
        Program grants G76003, G77325. Establishment of Alternate Media Center to experiment with cable television programming. $260,000, awarded on March 16, 1971. Program grant. To provide support for the Alternate Media Center. $325,000, awarded on March 15, 1973. Program grant. Support of diversifying and increasing sources of support for the Center. $60,000 fy 1978, awarded on June 14, 1977.
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, 1970-January 1975 (Box 49, Folder 354)
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, 1970-January 1975 (Box 49, Folder 355)
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, 1970-January 1975 (Box 49, Folder 356)
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, 1970-January 1975 (Box 49, Folder 357)
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, February 1975-1979 (Box 50, Folder 358)
        Program grants G76003, G77325. Establishment of Alternate Media Center to experiment with cable television programming. $260,000, awarded on March 16, 1971. Program grant. To continue experiments with innovative applications of telecommunications technology. $200,000 ($100,000 fy 1976, $100,000 fy 1977), awarded June 20, 1975.
      - New York University - Red Burns and George Stoney, February 1975-1979 (Box 50, Folder 359)
      - New York University - Robert Sklar, 1975-1978 (Box 50, Folder 360)
        Discretionary grant D78120. Cultural history of American television. Support of research for a book by Professor Robert Sklar entitled, "Video-Land: Television and American Culture." $4,950, awarded on October 6, 1977.
      - North Carolina - Department of Administration - Lee Wing, 1977-1983 (Box 50, Folder 361)
        Program grant G78209. For a comprehensive study of the current status of public telecommunications in North Carolina to evaluate new developments in telecommunications & recommend legislative and administrative changes. $82,677 ($41,677 fy 1978, $41,000 fy 1979), awarded on March 22, 1978.
      - North Carolina - Department of Administration - Lee Wing, 1977-1983 (Box 50, Folder 362)
      - North Carolina - Department of Administration - Lee Wing, 1977-1983 (Box 50, Folder 363)
      - University of North Carolina - William Gormley, 1974-1976 (Box 50, Folder 364)
        Program grant. To conduct a study to determine the effects of cross-media ownership on state and local news content. $20,425, awarded on November 22, 1974.
      - University of North Carolina - Stuart Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 51, Folder 365)
        Program grant. Southern Medical School Consortium Self-Instructional Project. $75,000, awarded on November 12, 1971.
      - University of North Carolina - Stuart Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 51, Folder 366)
      - Northwestern University - John Cooper, 1964 (Box 51, Folder 367)
        Medical School library.
      - Northwestern University - Robert Pekurney, 1979 (Box 51, Folder 368)
        Discretionary grant D79374. Observation of network programming - "Saturday Night Live." Support of "A Participant - Observation Study of a Network Program Production Company." $2,670, awarded June 5, 1979.
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1973-1976 (Box 51, Folder 369)
        Program grants D75029, G76060. Survey of television audiences. To conduct exploratory research on the identification of special interest audiences for public television. $38,500, awarded on November 22, 1974. Program grant. support of a pilot research study on the identification of special interest audiences for public television. $130,000 fy 1976, awarded on September 29, 1975. Program grant G77324. Support of a national study of audiences for television. $360,000 ($250,000 fy 1978, $110,000 fy 1979), awarded June 14, 1977.
        General note
        Grant number could be 760006 or 766060.
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1973-1976 (Box 51, Folder 370)
        Program grants D75029, G76060. Survey of television audiences. To conduct exploratory research on the identification of special interest audiences for public television. $38,500, awarded on November 22, 1974. Program grant. support of a pilot research study on the identification of special interest audiences for public television. $130,000 fy 1976, awarded on September 29, 1975. Program grant G77324. Support of a national study of audiences for television. $360,000 ($250,000 fy 1978, $110,000 fy 1979), awarded June 14, 1977.Program grant. support of a pilot research study on the identification of special interest audiences for public television. $130,000 fy 1976, awarded on September 29, 1975.
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1973-1976 (Box 51, Folder 371)
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1977-1981 (Box 52, Folder 372)
        Survey of television audiences.
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1977-1981 (Box 52, Folder 373)
      - University of Pennsylvania - Ronald Frank and Marshall Greenberg, 1977-1981 (Box 52, Folder 374)
      - University of Pennsylvania - William Moody, 1972-1974 (Box 52, Folder 375)
        Discretionary grant. Economic alternatives for children's programming. Study of economic implications of removing advertising from children's television. $13,000, awarded on August 17, 1972.
      - University of Pennsylvania - Martin Meyerson, 1974-1984 (Box 52, Folder 376)
        Discretionary grant D78334. French-American television conferences. Support of Franco-American symposium concerning the artistic dimensions of television. $5,000, awarded on May 23, 1978.
      - University of Pittsburgh - Carolyn Nemeyer, 1974-1976 (Box 52, Folder 377)
        Discretionary grant. Education for publishing. Partial support of the 2nd phase of a study of education for the book publishing industry conducted by the Association of American Publishers. $4,450, awarded on April 21, 1975.
      - Planning Corporation for the Arts - Theodora Sklover, 1970-1972 (Box 52, Folder 378)
        Program grant. Planning Grant for Community Cable Television Origination. $18,900, awarded on June 18, 1971.
      - Pomona College - Monica Morris, 1976-1977 (Box 53, Folder 379)
        Program grant. To support production of a pilot television program of entertainment and information for the elderly. $23,317 ($11,000 fy 1976, $12,317 fy 1977), awarded on March 12, 1976.
      - Population Education, Inc. - Elizabeth Roberts, 1975-1980 (Box 53, Folder 380)
        Program grant G77005. Support of a workshop for members of the television industry and public for the purpose of clarifying and seeking resolution to questions related to televised sexuality. $75,000 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976. Program grant G77327. Support of a series of West Coast workshops for television's creative community and to hold meetings with representatives of network affiliates in order to begin discussion of a wide range of topics related to television and sexuality. $100,000 ($75,000 fy 1978, $25,000 fy 1979), awarded on March 7, 1977. Discretionary grant D76010. Funds for planning a producer's workshop on the subject of stereotyping of sexual roles on television. $3,000, awarded on February 17, 1976. Discretionary grant D79373. Operating expenses for fy 1979. $15,000, awarded on May 1979.
      - Population Education, Inc. - Elizabeth Roberts, 1975-1980 (Box 53, Folder 381)
      - Population Education, Inc. - Elizabeth Roberts, 1975-1980 (Box 53, Folder 382)
      - Population Education, Inc. - Elizabeth Roberts, 1975-1980 (Box 53, Folder 383)
      - Press-Enterprise - Norman Cherniss, 1972-1976 (Box 53, Folder 384)
        Discretionary grant. For establishment of a press council. $6,600, awarded on October 24, 1973.
      - Princeton University - Fritz Machlup, 1976-1978 (Box 53, Folder 385)
        Program grant G77008. Support of an economic study of all industries that comprise the media of communications. $67,136 fy 1977, awarded on June 25, 1976.
      - Commission on Private Philanthropy and Public Needs - Leonard Silverstein, 1974-1978 (Box 54, Folder 386)
        Program grant. For a study of philanthropy, its relationship to government and its role in American society. $25,000, awarded on November 22, 1974.
      - Public Agenda Foundation - John Immerwahr, 1978-1981 (Box 54, Folder 387)
        Program grant G79252. To develop a profile of public and leadership attitudes about freedom of expression in the mass media and disseminate the findings. $175,000 ($40,000 fy 1979, $10,000 fy 1980, $25,000 fy 1981), awarded on March 22, 1979.
      - Public Agenda Foundation - John Immerwahr, 1978-1981 (Box 54, Folder 388)
      - Public Agenda Foundation - Daniel Yankelovich, 1977-1978 (Box 54, Folder 389)
        Program grant G77328. Support of a feasibility study to determine if there is a demand among potential users for the Public Agenda's work and if so to determine what role the media are willing and able to play in the dissemination process. $20,000 fy 1978, awarded on June 14, 1977.
      - Public Agenda Foundation - Daniel Yankelovich, 1977-1978 (Box 54, Folder 390)
      - Race Relations Information Center - James Leeson, 1972-1975 (Box 54, Folder 391)
        Program grant. Support for three seminars on race relations reporting. $50,000, awarded on March 12, 1974.
      - Rand Corporation - Franz Allina, 1969-1973 (Box 54, Folder 392)
        Program grant. Study of cable television regulation. $45,000, awarded on October 22, 1969.
      - Rand Corporation - Leland Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 55, Folder 393)
        Program grant. Communications policy issues. Support for research in cable television policy. $500,000, awarded on June 11, 1970. Program grant. Support for program of studies of communications policy issue. $350,000, awarded on June 15, 1973.
      - Rand Corporation - Leland Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 55, Folder 394)
      - Rand Corporation - Leland Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 55, Folder 395)
      - Rand Corporation - Leland Johnson, 1970-1976 (Box 55, Folder 396)
      - Rand Corporation - Robert Yin, 1973-1977 (Box 55, Folder 397)
        Program grant G76009. Evaluation of children's television network. Beginning research on identifying and measuring the size of special interest audiences for public television. $35,000, awarded on June 11, 1974. Program grant. Support of studies of communications policy issues. $100,000 ($50,000 fy 1976, $50,000 fy 1977), awarded on November 10, 1975. Discretionary grant. For a feasibility study of new evaluation methods for "Sesame Street" and "The Electric Company." $6,925, awarded on June 8, 1973. Discretionary grant. To publish and distribute a study of new evaluation methods for Children's Television Workshop programs. $2,500, awarded on September 12, 1973.
      - Rand Corporation - Robert Yin, 1973-1977 (Box 55, Folder 398)
      - Regional Plan Association - Mike McManus, 1970-1975 (Box 56, Folder 399)
        Program grant. Support for evaluation of "Choices for '76" television series. $50,000, awarded on March 15, 1973.
      - Regional Plan Association - Mike McManus, 1970-1975 (Box 56, Folder 400)
      - Regional Plan Association - Mike McManus, 1970-1975 (Box 56, Folder 401)
      - Regional Plan Association - Mike McManus, 1970-1975 (Box 56, Folder 402)
      - Regional Plan Association - Mike McManus, 1970-1975 (Box 56, Folder 403)
      - Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press - Jack Landau, 1976-1977 (Box 56, Folder 404)
        Program grant G78211. For a program to strengthen existing services and extend fundraising activities. $71,460 ($10,000 fy 1978, $41,460 fy 1979, $20,000 fy 1980), awarded on March 22, 1978.
      - Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press - Jack Landau, 1978-1981 (Box 57, Folder 405)
      - Reporters Committee for Freedom of the Press - Jack Landau, 1978-1981 (Box 57, Folder 406)
      - Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene - Allen Miller, 1975 (Box 57, Folder 407)
        Patient orientation film.
      - Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene - David Wilder, 1974-1975 (Box 57, Folder 408)
        Discretionary grant D75021. Patient orientation film. For an evaluation of the films produced with Foundation funds for the orientation of hospital patients. $4,895, awarded on December 20, 1974. Discretionary grant D75030. To cover costs of evaluating MF's Medical Project. $11,396, awarded on June 5, 19795.
      - Research Foundation for Mental Hygiene - David Wilder, 1974-1975 (Box 57, Folder 409)
      - Research Foundation of the State University of New York Stony Brook - Kurt Lang, 1974-1981 (Box 57, Folder 410)
        Discretionary grant D75019. Mass media and Watergate. For support of a study of the relationship between the mass media and the Watergate controversy. $5,000, awarded on November 22, 1974.
      - University of Richmond - Robert Alley and Irby Brown, 1977-1978 (Box 57, Folder 411)
        Program grant G79254. Television workshops. To conduct research, organize a conference, and write a book about the relationship between television and the family over the last three decades of American life. $64,885 ($10,000 fy 1979, $54,885 fy 1980), awarded on March 22, 1979.
      - University of Richmond - Robert Alley and Irby Brown, 1979 (Box 58, Folder 412)
        Television workshops.
      - University of Richmond - Robert Alley and Irby Brown, 1979 (Box 58, Folder 413)
      - Roswell Park Memorial Institute - Gerald Murphy, 1954-1972 (Box 58, Folder 414)
        Health Research, Inc.
      - Rutgers University - Jerome Aumente, 1972-1983 (Box 58, Folder 415)
        Program grant G79368. To conduct a seminar-workshop for television critics. $40,000 fy 1980, awarded on June 14, 1979.
      - Rutgers University - Jerome Aumente, 1972-1983 (Box 58, Folder 416)
      - Rutgers University - Jerome Aumente, 1972-1983 (Box 58, Folder 417)
      - University of Saskatchewan - John Gutelius, 1969-1971 (Box 59, Folder 418)
        Discretionary grant. Funds to recruit new staff. $3,000, awarded on December 2, 1969.
      - Senate of the State of New York - Michael Ruberti, 1973-1975 (Box 59, Folder 419)
        Program grant. For a conference on the appropriate role of state governments in cable television regulation. $20,000, awarded on November 5, 1973. Discretionary grant. For a conference on the appropriate role of state governments in cable television regulation. $20,000, awarded on November 5, 1973.
      - Senate of the State of New York - Michael Ruberti, 1973-1975 (Box 59, Folder 420)
      - Social Science Research Council - Warren E. Miller, 1974 (Box 59, Folder 420A)
        Mass communications and political behavior.
      - Social Science Research Council - Sidney Kraus, 1973-1979 (Box 59, Folder 421)